A Finding Aid to the John Steuart Curry and Curry Family Papers, 1848-1999, bulk 1916-1946, in the Archives of American Art AAA.currjohn
Archives of American Art
John Steuart Curry and Curry family papers
1848-1999
AAA.currjohn
Archives of American Art
9.2 Linear feet
The papers of painter, muralist, and illustrator John Steuart Curry, and Curry family papers, measure 9.2 linear feet and date from 1848 to 1999. Papers document his career and family history through certificates, correspondence, photographs, clippings, contracts, receipts, inventories, writings, notes, and other materials. The papers contain particularly rich documentation of Curry's period as artist-in-residence at the University of Wisconsin, from 1936 to 1946. Mural projects in Kansas, Washington, DC, and Wisconsin are also documented.
Curry, John Steuart, 1897-1946
Provenance
Papers were lent for microfilming in 1971 by Curry's widow, Kathleen Curry. In 1979 she subsequently donated portions of the loaned material, along with additional material, which was microfilmed upon receipt. The home movies were donated in 1973 by Ellen Schuster, Curry's daughter. Additional papers were donated in 1972 and 1975 by Mildred Curry Fike, Curry's sister; in 1975 and 1993 by R. Eugene Curry, his brother; in 1991 by Daniel Schuster, his son-in-law; and in 1995, 1999, and 2000 by Kathleen Curry.
Separated Material
A 1992 loan by Kathleen Curry included 98 Sketchbooks of Curry's, dated from 1919-1942; a ledger, 1938-1946, of expenses with four loose letters to Curry in italian and spanish; a notebook, 1932-1938, titled "Account and records of works, etc."; a notebook, undated, of drafts of poems, and approximately 50 sketches. Materials in this loan were microfilmed on reels 4574-4576 and sealed under Mrs. Curry's death in 2001. Originals of loaned material were returned to the donor after microfilming.
Curry memorabilia received with the Kathleen Curry's donation in 1979 (baby cup, baby dress, overalls, medals, paint box, watercolor box, 2 photographs) were transferred to the Spencer Museum of Art in 1985.
Portions of Kathleen Curry's initial 1971 loan were not subsequently donated. The entire loan can be viewed on reels 164-168.
Location of Originals
Materials loaned by Mrs. Curry in 1971 for microfilming were returned to the donor, who later donated the sketchbooks to the Worcester Museum of Art in 1999.
Related Material
The Archives of American Art holds an oral history interview with Kathleen Curry regarding John Steuart Curry conducted in 1990 and 1992.
Alternative Forms Available
The papers of John Steuart Curry and the Curry Family in the Archives of American Art were digitized in 2007, and total 10872 images.
Types of materials not digitized or partially digitized include published books and pamphlets, personal financial records unrelated to artwork, photographs of works of art, estate files related to projects and exhibitions dated after 1985, duplicate items, and copies.
Restrictions on Access
The bulk of the collection has been digitized and is available online via AAA's website. Access to undigitized portions requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Painter, muralist, and illustrator John Steuart Curry is considered one of the three important painters of the American Regionalist movement, along with Thomas Hart Benton of Missouri and Grant Wood of Iowa. Curry was born in north-eastern Kansas in 1897, and grew up on his family's farm. Curry left high school to attend the Kansas City Art Institute briefly, and then studied at the Art Institute of Chicago in 1916 with Edward J. Timmons and John Norton. Curry later spent a year in Paris studying with Basil Schoukhaieff in 1926 and 1927.
Curry began his career as a freelance illustrator in Leonia, New Jersey, under the influence of Harvey Dunn. Curry's illustrations were widely published in illustrated magazines such as Boy's Life, Country Gentleman, and Saturday Evening Post in the early 1920s. He married Clara Derrick in 1923 and lived in Greenwich Village, and then Westport, Connecticut, from 1924 to 1936. Derrick died in 1932, and in 1934 Curry married Kathleen Gould.
Curry's career shifted from illustration to painting during the 1920s and 1930s, bolstered by success in exhibitions and sales. Exhibits included the National Academy of Design (1924), the Corcoran Gallery (1927-1928), a solo exhibition at the Whitney Studio Club (1930), and the Carnegie International Exhibition (1933). Early sales include Baptism in Kansas, purchased by the Whitney in 1930, and Spring Shower, purchased by the Metropolitan Museum in 1932. Curry taught at Cooper Union (1932-1934) and the Art Student's League (1932-1934), and painted his first murals in Westport under the Federal Art Project in 1934.
In 1936, he was appointed artist-in-residence at the University of Wisconsin College of Agriculture as part of a rural art program developed by rural sociologist John Burton. The purpose of his residency was to serve as an educational resource for rural people of the state. Curry stayed in this position until his death in 1946, carrying out the program's mission through lectures and visits with dozens of art and civic groups around the state, and by making himself available to rural artists through correspondence and guidance in his studio. He also helped to organize annual rural art exhibitions for UW's Farm and Home Week beginning in 1940. In return for his work, he was given a salary and a studio on campus and the freedom to execute his own work as he chose.
Under the Federal Art Program's Section of Painting and Sculpture, Curry completed two murals in the Justice Department building in Washington in 1936, Westward Migration and Justice Defeating Mob Violence, and two murals in the Department of the Interior building in 1938, The Homestead and The Oklahoma Land Rush. A design that was rejected by the government for the Justice building, a mural entitled Freeing of the Slaves, was later executed at the University of Wisconsin in their law library. From 1938 to 1940, Curry worked on murals for the state house rotunda in Topeka, Kansas admist a stormy, public controversy over his dramatic depiction of Kansas history. The legislature effectively blocked Curry's completion of the project through a formal resolution not to remove marble that was blocking areas that were part of Curry's design. Infuriated, Curry left the unfinished murals unsigned, and later derided the state frequently for the treatment he received. The Kansas State legislature issued a formal apology and appreciation of the completed murals in the 1990s.
Despite the lack of appreciation of his home state, Curry did receive recognition elsewhere during his lifetime as an artist of national importance. He continued to paint and exhibit in the art centers of the East Coast. In 1941, he won the Gold Medal Award at the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts exhibition, and in the 1942 Artists For Victory exhibition, he won the top prize for Wisconsin Landscape. Curry's book illustrations were in high demand, and he contributed to books such as My Friend Flicka, editions of Lincoln's and Emerson's writings, and Wisconsin writer August Derleth's The Wisconsin. A biography of Curry written by Laurence Schmeckebier was published in 1942.
Curry died in 1946 of heart failure. A retrospective that had been planned for the living artist opened less than a month after his death at the Milwaukee Art Institute. His wife, Kathleen Curry, maintained his estate until her death, in 2001, at the age of 102. Additional retrospective exhibitions were held at Syracuse University in 1956 and in the Kansas State Capitol in 1970. In 1998, the exhibition "John Steuart Curry: Inventing the Middle West" was organized at the University of Wisconsin and traveled to the M.H. de Young Memorial Museum and the Nelson Atkins Museum of Art.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of painter, muralist, and illustrator John Steuart Curry, and Curry family papers, measure 9.2 linear feet and date from 1848 to 1999. Papers document his career and family history through certificates, correspondence, photographs, clippings, contracts, receipts, inventories, writings, notes, and other materials. The papers contain particularly rich documentation of Curry's period as artist-in-residence at the University of Wisconsin, from 1936 to 1946. Mural projects in Kansas, Washington, DC, and Wisconsin are also documented.
Biographical Materials include chronologies, biographical narratives, genealogical notes, certificates and awards, and other ephemera related to Curry and his family. Family Correspondence includes the earliest records created by Curry himself, including letters home from art school and from the East Coast during his early career.
Correspondence and Project files document mural projects, appearances, gallery relationships, and other activities from the early 1930s until his death in 1946 with correspondence, photographs, clippings, contracts, writings, and other miscellany. Subject files include pictorial reference and research files created by Curry for subjects depicted in his murals and paintings. Curry's writings include essays, lectures, interviews, and notes related to his technical and philosophical approach to art, as well as notes from his various travels, and essays by others about Curry. Personal Business Records contain records of artwork, business transactions, and personal finances.
Print Materials include print copies of published artwork by Curry, including magazine illustrations from Curry's early career. Extensive clippings, exhibition catalogs, and a scrapbook created by Curry as a youth are also found. Photographs depict Curry throughout his life in formal portraits, candid snapshots, and publicity photographs, with a significant number of photographs depicting Curry creating and posing with his artwork. The Artwork series contains a few sketches by Curry and seven canvases used for testing art materials. Additional sketches are found in Subject Files and scrapbooks.
Estate Papers contain materials dated after Curry's death in 1946 and mainly document the activities of Kathleen Curry in managing her husband's estate from 1946 until her death in 2001. Estate papers contain writings about Curry, correspondence, inventories of artwork, and alphabetical files documenting sales, exhibitions, and other projects.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into ten series:
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1911-1993 (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 2: Family Correspondence, 1916-1946 (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 3: Correspondence and Project Files, 1928-1946 (Boxes 1-3, OV 11; 2.3 linear feet)
Series 4: Subject Files, 1848-1946 (Boxes 3-4, OV 11-12; 0.7 linear feet)
Series 5: Notes and Writings, circa 1911-1946 (Box 4; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 6: Personal Business Records, 1916-1952 (Box 4, OV 13; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 7: Print Materials, 1918-1985 (Boxes 4-5, 10; OV 12-13; 1.6 linear feet)
Series 8: Photographs, circa 1900-1998 (Boxes 5-6, OV 14; 1.1 linear feet)
Series 9: Artwork, 1941, undated (Box 7, OV 12, 14, 15; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 10: Estate Papers, circa 1946-1999 (Boxes 7-9 and rolled document; 2.3 linear feet)
Curry, Kathleen, 1899-; Art--Study and teaching; Art--Technique; Illustrators--Wisconsin; Interviews; Muralists--Wisconsin; Painters--Wisconsin; Photographs; Regionalism in art; Scrapbooks; Sketches; Video recordings; Works of art
- Biographical Materials, 1911-1993; Series 1; (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains certificates, a chronology of Curry's life, biographical narratives for encyclopedias, family history research and genealogical charts, school records, a video copy of home movies, and documents related to family members of John Steuart Curry.
  Genealogical information appears to have been compiled by Curry's brother, R. Eugene Curry. The home movies are approximately eight minutes long and include footage of Curry around 1938 on horseback with a group of unidentified people in the mountains, and his daughter, wife, and pets playing in the yard.
  Additional writings about John Steuart Curry are found in Notes and Writings and Estate Papers.
  - Awards and Membership Certificates, 1933-1942 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chronology, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Encyclopedia Entries, circa 1936-1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Genealogy and Family History, circa 1943-1993 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - High School Report Card and Grammar School Graduation Card, 1911, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Home Movies (circa 1938), 1991; (8 minutes; VHS copy of 8mm film original; not digitized) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Obituary for Paul Curry, circa 1927 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ellen Curry Print Material, circa 1941 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Family Correspondence, 1916-1946; Series 2; (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
  This series contains correspondence between John Steuart Curry and members of his family, as well as letters among family members, written before his death in 1946. Curry's letters include detailed, early letters from Chicago during his first years of art school, and letters from Leonia, NJ and Greenwich Village during his early career. Scattered illustrations by Curry are found in these early letters. Two folders also contain notes about Curry's letters written by the family members who donated them to the Archives. Similar notes are found in Estate Papers.
  Letters written by Kathleen Curry are to Margery Curry, Curry's sister. Letters from Margaret Curry are mainly addressed to John. Letters among family members after Curry's death in 1946 are found in the Estate Papers.
  Arrangement note
  Letters are filed by author.
  - John Steuart Curry, 1916-1923, 1926, 1942; (8 folders) (Box 1, Folder 9-16)
    (includes one letter from Curry's first wife, Clara, to his parents following their marriage in 1923; last letter dated 1922 is a photocopy, location of original is unknown)
  - Kathleen Curry, 1937, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    (Includes letters to Margery Curry, JSC's sister)
  - Margaret Curry (mother), 1938-1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - R. Eugene Curry (brother), 1938, 1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Derrick Family, circa 1932, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous Family Correspondence, circa 1928-1944 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Correspondence and Project Files, 1928-1946; Series 3; (Boxes 1-3, OV 11; 2.3 linear feet)
  This series contains correspondence and other materials related to Curry's position as Artist in Residence at the University of Wisconsin (1936-1946), other professional projects during that period, and scattered earlier correspondence and print material. Other types of documents found include receipts, invoices, lists of artwork, clippings, photographs, blueprints, and other miscellany. Documents are arranged alphabetically by personal name, corporate name, subject, or project. Substantial files are found for galleries that represented Curry, including Maynard Walker's Ferargil Gallery, Walker Galleries, and Associated American Artists. Curry's major mural projects are documented under the headings "Kansas State House Murals," "Treasury Department, Section of Painting and Sculpture," and University of Wisconsin. Illustration jobs are filed by title or publisher under the heading Book Illustration.
  Background documentation for Curry's appointment as artist-in-residence in the agricultural college at the University of Wisconsin is found in the University of Wisconsin files, including writings and research materials related to the "Rural Art" program he served there. Throughout the series, correspondence with art students, art teachers, aspiring artists, art clubs, and other civic clubs in Wisconsin and throughout the midwest reflect his role in this initiative.
  Arrangement is idiosyncratic. In general, letters are filed alphabetically by organization or corporate name, if applicable. Place names for schools and civic clubs are common access points. Names with five or more letters are filed in their own folders, and the remainder of correspondence is filed in miscellaneous files. Selected correspondents whose names do not appear in headings are indicated in a note following the folder heading. Materials other than correspondence are also noted in the folder listing.
  - Miscellaneous A, 1938-1946 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Abbott Laboratories, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Allen, Mr. and Mrs. Henry J., 1931, 1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    (See also Kansas State House Murals)
  - American Academy in Rome, 1941-1944 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - American Artists Group, 1936-1946, 1950; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
  - American Association of University Women -- Green Bay, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - American Association of University Women -- Superior, WI, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Army Medical Department Art Project, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Art Institute of Chicago, 1942, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    (Daniel Cotton Rich)
  - Art Reference Round Table, American Library Association, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Artext Prints, Inc., 1938-1941, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Associated Amateur Art Clubs, circa 1929-1939 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Associated American Artists, 1937-1946; (16 folders) (Box 1, Folder 35-50)
    (Reeves Lewenthal, Thomas Mabry, Treasury Department, Francis Henry Taylor)
  - Associated American Artists, Receipts, 1938-1946; (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 51-53)
  - Associated American Artists, Prospect List, Chicago, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Miscellaneous B, 1936-1946 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    (letter to Peyton Boswell, letter from Mrs. Henry Breckenridge)
  - Ball, David, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Barloga, Viola, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Beggs, Thomas M. (Pamona College), 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Beloit College, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Benton, Thomas Hart, 1937-1945, undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
    (contains technical notes and recipes, draft of Benton's review of JSC Pageant of America, a 1937 catalog, and an illustrated pamphlet by Benton entitled "The Year of Peril"; see also Estate Papers for correspondence between Benton and Kathleen Curry)
  - Book Illustration Projects (Box 1)
    - Book of the Month Club, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 61)
      (Harry Abrams, The Complete Essays and Other Writings of Ralph Waldo Emerson, My Friend Flicka, Thunderhead; also contains promotional pamphlet for Flicka and Thunderhead)
    - Divine Comedy, 1943-1946 (Box 1, Folder 62)
      (A. Tedesco and Doubleday, Doran, and Co.)
    - J.F. Cooper's "The Prairie", 1937-1941, undated (Box 1, Folder 63)
      (George Macy, William Kitteridge; also contains contract)
    - John Brown's Body, circa 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 64)
      (George Macy, Limited Editions Club; also contains contract)
    - Leaves of Grass, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 65)
      (Peter Bailenson, Peter Pauper Press)
    - The Literary Works of Abraham Lincoln, circa 1938-1942; (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 66-68)
      (George Macy, Limited Editions Club; also contains contract, research material, clippings, fan mail, typescripts draft and table of contents)
    - The Red Badge of Courage, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Tall Book of Bible Stories, 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 70)
      (Lucille Ogle, Artists and Writers Guild; cotains typescript list of illustrations)
    - The Wisconsin, 1940-1943 (Box 1, Folder 71)
      (August Derleth, Farrar and Rinehart; contains photographs)
  - Brittingham, Thomas E., 1937-1946 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    (contains press release regarding Brittingham donation to fund Curry's mural in the Biochemistry Building, U. Wisconsin; see also University of Wisconsin)
  - Bruce, Edward (see Treasury Department) (Box 2)
  - Butler Art Institute, 1941-1944 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous C, 1931-1946 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    (Senator Arthur Capper, CBS, Cincinnati Art Museum (Walter Siple), Wilford Conrow, Cooper Union School of Art)
  - Carnegie Institute, 1937-1946 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    (John O'Connor, Homer Saint Gaudens)
  - Chappell, Warren, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Christensen, Chris L., 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    (see also University of Wisconsin)
  - Christ-Janer, Albert, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Corcoran Gallery of Art/Corcoran School of Art, 1937-1945 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    (C. Powell Minnigerode, Dick Lahey)
  - Craven, Thomas, circa 1935-1946 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous D-E, 1928, 1939-1945 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    (Dayton Art Institute, James Daugherty)
  - Dance Players, Inc., 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    (Eugene Loring, Winthrop B. Palmer; concerning decorations for a ballet of Carl Sandburg's "The Prairie")
  - Davis, Vachel, 1940-1945; (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
  - Dodd, Lamar, circa 1939-1945 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Educational Policies Commission, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Encyclopedia Brittanica, 1943-1946 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    (also contains receipts)
  - Esquire Magazine, 1938-1943 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    (Eric Lundgren and Arnold Gingrich)
  - Miscellaneous F, 1937-1946 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    (Hulda Reiter Fischer)
  - F.W. Weber Co., 1929-1946; (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 19-20)
    (also contains technical bulletins about art materials and receipts)
  - Farr, Helen "Pete" (later Sloan), 1935, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
    (contains technical notes)
  - Ferargil Galleries, circa 1930-1935; (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 22-24)
    (Maynard Walker, W. H. White, Mateel Howe Farnham; contains article by Farnham about Curry)
  - Ferargil Galleries, Financial Statements, 1931-1935 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - First National Bank (Madison, Wisconsin) Murals, 1940-1944 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    (also contains contract)
  - Fortney, Vivian, 1939-1942 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Fults, Louise C., 1943 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Miscellaneous G, 1938-1946 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    (McLeod M. Pearce of Geneva College regarding Curry's honorary degree; Henry Allen Moe of the Guggenheim Foundation)
  - Garrison, Lloyd, 1940-1946 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    (See also Estate Papers)
  - Gilbertson, Boris, 1941-1945 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Miscellaneous H, 1936-1945 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    (Oskar Hagen, Sidney Howard, Marion Humfield)
  - Hibbs, Ben ( Country Gentleman), 1941 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Hodgell Family, 1941-1946 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    (Ray, Robert, and Murlin Hodgell)
  - Miscellaneous I-J, 1937-1945 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    (Fritz Jochem, Wilbur Peat of John Herron Art Institute)
  - Janesville Art League (Wisconsin), 1942-1944 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Miscellenous K, 1937-1946 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Kalamazoo Institute of Arts, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Kansas State House Murals, circa 1937-1943; (8 folders) (Box 2, Folder 39-46)
    (Jack Harris, Beth Dickerson, Roy Stookey, Reeves Lewenthal, Henry Allen, Fred Crittenden (see also Misc. C), Henry Carey, Ted Wear and article by Wear, Walter Jones, Olle Nordmark, W.A. White, H.G. Lull, Senator Arthur Capper, Paul Jones, Ray Hodgell, Raymond Eastwood, Tulsa Tribune, Albert Cole, Maynard Walker; contains receipts and 1941 state resolution blocking further work on the murals; see also Henry J. Allen, John Helm, Jr., and Sam Nock)
  - Kansas State House Murals, Narrative Description and Contract (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Kansas State Federation of Art, 1935-1944 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    (John Helm, Jr.)
  - Kappa Pi, Honorary Art Fraternity, circa 1942-1944 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Katona, Verna Wendelin and Arthur, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Kittredge, William A., 1938-1944 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    (See also book Illustrations)
  - Knickerbocker, Laura, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    (Topeka Community Art Center; see also Kansas State House Murals)
  - Kuniyoshi, Yasuo, circa 1941, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Miscellaenous L, 1937-1946 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    (Clare Leighton, Starker Leopold, F. Jochem of Louisiana State)
  - Layton School of Art, 1938-1941 (Box 2, Folder 55)